[music]
Um so hi I'm Jennifer Sans. I'm CEO and
co-founder at a company called
Codential. Uh my background is actually
in largecale uh very distributed uh SAS
environments typically in for mission
critical applications. So previously I
was uh VP of product at a cloud security
startup called cloud lock which we
exited to Cisco and then after that I
led the product strategy at a company
called Everbridge which is responsible
for tracking and managing global
physical and digital threats for some of
the largest enterprises and governments
in the world. So given that background
uh and the experiences that we had
there, that's what we're bringing to
credential to build an AI code
verification solution uh to make sure
that the types of issues that we're
going to describe today don't leak out
into production environments as we have
experienced them throughout our careers.
>> Thanks Jennifer. My name is Brandy. I've
worked in the industry for quite a
while. I've worked at companies of
various sizes. I was with Jennifer at
Cloud Lock into Cisco for a number of
years. I worked at toast leading large
engineering teams working on delivery
meaning food delivery not just software
delivery uh and I have a background
generally in deep tech area
architectures patterns and verification
and so so happy to be presenting what
we've been working on to to all of you.
So what we're going to talk about today
is less about a demo of our product
which we're happy to do later offline um
but also uh some of the core tenants
that are driving uh what we're building
and why we're doing it. So based on the
years of experience delivering these
types of mission critical uh systems,
what we have learned is that despite all
of the QA methodologies and solutions
and headcounts and everything that we
throw towards code quality, there is
some types of issues that always still
seem to make it out into production. And
usually those are the issues that wake
up your on call engineers at 3:00 am and
send your uh largest enterprise customer
screaming at you and your engineering
team on a three-week death march to try
to root cause what happened, why it
happened, and how you can prevent it. So
the reason why these things happen is
because testing does not capture or
catch these types of issues because
testing is focused on identifying uh
specific test cases and it misses a lot
of edge cases and concurrency issues
that only occur in real world scenarios
when codebase beats infrastructure meets
your favorite enterprise customers data
etc. Um, and just because testing
doesn't find bugs when it's executed,
that does not mean that no bugs exist.
And so there are all these different
types of things that tests can often
miss. Um, and what we found is these are
also the types of issues that coding
agents will silently inject into the
code that's being created and then the
code may pass every functional test, but
these subtle architectural issues still
make their way into production. and then
you don't identify them until you've
forgotten about what the code was and
you shipped it and it's three months
later and then you have to go back and
fix all of that. Um, I want to point out
here also there is a bit.ly link here.
So, we're going to be walking through
some examples of the types of issues
that we're identifying in AI generated
code and we're going to show you a tool
that you can use today um and take home
with you to prevent uh AI agents from
generating that type of code in the
first place. And if you want to follow
along or if you want to access uh the
GitHub repo uh that we're leveraging for
the demo purposes, you can do that
through this uh bit.ly link that's going
to be on every slide uh as we progress.
So, let's talk about three categories of
very difficult to test problems. So, you
know, we're calling these untestable.
Um, and certainly like there's ways that
you could test for them, but it's not uh
it's not uh practical or pragmatic
necessarily to do so. So in a category
of too hard to test, uh, race conditions
is just a great example of that. So
being able to test for race conditions,
uh, requires that you think upfront
about what are the race conditions that
could occur and the variety of them and
then construct tests to do so, right?
Um, and then you have to have the luck
of the test exact executing perfectly in
order to trigger that, right? Um so
being able to test for that is too
difficult to actually like bother and
plan for um too expensive to test. So
you know everyone does performance
testing to some degree. We do load
testing. We do all the various kinds of
testing. Um those are really uh focused
on acute load in most cases and there's
so many different performance
characteristics that only show up under
sustained load on over a long period of
time. And we think about what would it
cost to actually replicate that in a
test environment. It requires duplicate
infrastructure, duplicate production
level data and the tooling in order to
generate that sustained load over time,
right? And that starts to become
prohibitively expensive, too complex to
test. Uh this is one of my favorites. So
combinatorial state explosions is a
super fun phrase to say. And um when you
think about all of the different
permutations and states that you're
managing in some scenarios, it means
that you would have to write so many
tests and execute so many tests uh for
all of those permutations that again uh
it becomes prohibitively expensive in
both manh hours and cost in order to do
so. So in these three categories of
bugs, uh what we're going to do is we're
going to walk through some specific
examples of uh what we can what we can
uh identify and then we're going to show
you a demo of a coding agent producing
uh uh code that creates these problems
followed by uh an example of the coding
agent being prevented from creating uh
these issues in code.
So, in the two hard to test category,
race conditions in transactions, we are
going to show you um an example just
super simple where if two users try to
buy the last item in uh stock
simultaneously or they encounter a soft
failure, right? So, in this case, um
tests can miss this primarily because uh
it could be a flaky test. it's an
intermittent failure typically in
testing. And so you're always going to
question, is this the test failing or is
this a real issue, right? And so every
time the test runs successfully, then
you're going to question that again. Um,
and it's really difficult to write
multi-threaded tests that could capture
that and then you would also have to
invest in the simulation of it, which
would require you to think about all of
the potential test cases up front. So,
uh, we're going to demo an example of
this type of too hard to test race
condition using, uh, two users
simultaneously, uh, purchasing
something.
The next example that we're going to
walk through is in the too expensive to
test category. So, some uh, performance
characteristics. And the example that
we're going to use is when you query
data from MongoDB without using lean and
it uh returns the data correctly. It's
functionally correct but it returns the
entire mongoose document as opposed to
just the plain JS object that you need
to display. Right? And so this is
something that will pass the test um and
you wouldn't necessarily detect it. And
even if you're doing some sort of
performance uh testing, test databases
are small and so the uh memory impact
would not necessarily be visible unless
you're doing a production uh data set
test, right? Um that would be uh
prohibitively expensive in a lot of
cases, especially at enterprise scale.
um and uh it would require uh a lot of
time to create that slow load where it
would in fact become a problem.
And then the other category in terms of
too complex to test the example that
we're going to leverage for this is
around um uh basically verifying the
validity of a product um at various
states. So when you're thinking if
someone's add something to the cart or
the user takes some action for each of
those actions you want to be able to
verify is this a valid product to
perform that action on. And that takes
into account not just is it available or
not. That's a super simplistic example.
Right? When you're thinking about
enterprisecale inventory states
especially with distributed warehousing
then you're in a situation where it
could be in stock or out of stock.
Certainly it could be discontinued. It
could be uh in transit to the warehouse.
It could be in all of these different
states. Then you have to think about the
the state of the cart. Um you have to
think about the uh different product
life cycle events. And then each of
these validations has to occur depending
on the user action. And so when you
start to multiply that out, you're now
in a situation where you have over 2500
possible permutations of things that you
would validate. And I don't know that
anyone is going to write 2500 different
tests to make sure that that is true. So
another example is we have a design
partner who we're working with that is
producing um uh software that allows
their users to create custom workflows,
very complex workflows. There's no
possible way that they can test for
every combination of workflow. So you
start to see where this appears in other
types of software as well.
So essentially what we're saying is uh
with invariance you can verify not just
does the code work but is it correct and
so historically we write code we write
tests the tests pass and we ship it.
Yay. Um and what we're saying is that
actually if you think upfront about the
things that must always be true and then
you instruct the agent to write code
that takes those things into account.
the agent writes the tests and then you
can verify that those things are in fact
still true. Then you can go through your
testing and your test pass and you ship.
So what we're going to introduce as a
mechanism to help guide the agent toward
code correctness is an invariant
verification taxonomy. So this allows
you to uh uh define the scope. So is
this universal across any codebase? Is
this just a a rule that everyone should
know that should be true or this is like
battle scars that engineers earn over
time based on their experience? Is this
something that is specific to your code
base or is this something that is
feature specific? So defining that scope
you can define the type of invariant
that it is whether it's
performance-based or logic based. And
then once that uh invariant is verified
uh when you're when you're or uh
violated when you're verifying it, what
should be done about it? Um does it just
send a warning? Does it fail uh
continuous integration? Um or do you ask
the agent to implement a fix?
So I'm going to play a video demo that
uh Bry's going to walk through in terms
of uh the uh show and tell here.
Yep.
>> That' be great. Thank you so much. So,
um, just show of hands. Who remembers
from maybe a computer science class
invariance?
Remember invarian? I got one, two, and
then how many people remembered
invariance after that semester? How many
use them actually after that one class?
I think I did them back uh away my
undergrad some algorithms class where we
had to do some invariance in some weird
language that did them and then they
kind of just fade in the background.
Well, they're here and they're real and
they actually really help when working
with agents. So, what we put together is
a simple shopping cart app. Everyone can
has access to the same source uh for
this. So, you can follow along look
afterwards uh through the app together
in cloud code as to generate test
coverage generate 100% test coverage and
well as we've seen obviously we're we
have a talk so it's not perfect. So, um
first one we're going to walk through is
the two hard to test. So this is the uh
reserve items method. So this is a key
method. It's a shopping cart. Shopping
cart has two two key pieces. I need to
get an item and I need to pay. So on the
reserve items, very straightforward
flow. I just back up here.
>> Yeah,
>> thanks.
>> Thank you. And just pause maybe.
>> Yeah,
>> thank you. Um so very simple
functionality. Uh find an item, check
the quantity, put a reservation in, and
then update Um, this works
perfectly fine, of course, until there's
an error. Notice it just returns false,
and there's no back out of a
reservation. Notice that if multiple
threads hit this at the same time, find
one returns one count, then the next
time another thread comes in, gets the
same count, then they both hit the same
time. Okay, very typical. Uh, we do a
lot of AI generated code. This is a very
typical pattern that comes in. And so,
let's see how we can address this. And
so, we can just sort of click along in
the Okay, there we go. So this is uh so
we're going to consider this a global
concern. So we want to make sure our
transactions are fine no matter
what project we're working on. Okay,
imagine if you work in Postgress or SQL,
you'd have an equivalent for this. So we
threw together this invariant.mmd. We
consider this the global one. So you
take this file and drop this into your
you know your your source your root
folder um some root agent folder. So
it's picked up by whatever agent there.
And there's a structure that that we
showed a little bit earlier. So we have
a description of what this issue is
about. Uh you can just advance a little
bit. There we go. Thank you. Um what
it's about. We give examples. We talk
about why this is important. So it's
important to tell the agent a positive
example and a counter example. So this
is what the good code looks like. This
is what the bad code looks like. And
then most importantly, we tell it here's
how to verify that this is correct.
Okay. So there's a whole lot of
different methods you can choose to
verify and it's going to depend on the
actual severity and criticality of this
to your organization. Okay, this one
getting transactions right this seems
pretty important. So we want to make
sure that we're actually checking this
properly. So we saw from the prior talk
that if you just use the same agent and
say hey does this violate transaction
stuff, you're not really sure what
you're going to get. So, we threw
together a little MCP server that just
gets this uh trans called transaction
analyzer does some very hacky regex on
transactions and then sees what it's
about and returns information back. So,
you'll notice that we ran this over the
code. Claude talks a lot about if we
found this issue in this spot, this
spot, this spot, didn't find it here,
what do you want to do for a fix? Okay.
And then it's set up there so as you
generate more code, it's going to start
invoking that MCP server at the right
time and get you the feedback. Okay, the
next one we're going on to is the too
expensive to test. So, let's just uh
fast forward to where it drops into the
uh zooms into the So, too expensive to
test. This is the one where it just it's
perfectly fine and it's fine maybe for
months and months and months in
production till all of a sudden you hit
Black Friday and you're out of memory on
your servers. So, um so we we use
Mongoose on our own system and this is
just this happens very easily. It
generates great queries and it
forgets.lean on readon. Solean strips
everything out. Um it just very
performant much easier. But in this case
it calls exec and then immediately calls
two object and so that creates u you
know a bigger memory blip. Uh very
typical pattern. Uh again this happens
to us in our own code until we put this
in and now it doesn't happen. So let's
fast forward. So we generate in
invariant for this. We're going to
consider this a project scope. Not every
project we use has mongus in it. And so
we don't want to just sort of mess up
our global context. So let's just put it
into our project context. Okay. Same
structure again. I'll go through a
little quick. We explain what this is
about, how to apply this. Examples of
looking bad, examples looking good. And
then um we'll fast forward and we get we
give this to Claude. We say, "Hey, go
take a look at this function with these
invariants. Tell me what you find." And
we'll see that um and again because this
is a little less critical, we just ask
Claude to do some code inspection like a
code review. Okay, so just look at the
generator code. We don't really need to
go out to another server or have a lot
of harder check. We'll just do some
review on it. And so it goes through it
finds a bunch of issues. Then we ask it
generate a new get items below price for
me. And we fast forward a little bit. It
generates it with the lean automatically
for us. And so showing that this has
been uh incorporated in. Okay. Third
example, the combinatoral state. So in
the bounds of the demo, I can't show you
a great way to check all 2586
states at once. But uh what we want to
do is make sure at the end of the day,
our system is not broke. Okay. So we
have the simple add item method. Again,
key part of a cart. And when we look at
this again, very simple demo app.
There's already a lot of validation that
happens. It's going to be a correct
item. Price has to be okay, not negative
quantities. Like there's like four or
five different checks in this. Um it's
not checking reserved items, not
checking stuff coming from the
warehouse. Those that's stuff that we'll
build out later in this. But what we
want from this invariant is we want to
make sure that whenever we're done with
the inventory that it's in a consistent
state. Whatever whatever operations
happened, it got there. We're just
putting in a back stop at the end. Okay.
So this is a different technique. So
we'll go ahead to the uh invariant again
explaining the same sort of stuff give
an example before and after and in this
case we want to do with some pre-save
and pre-update hooks. Okay, so showing a
different technique and so this way it's
a hook we can put into to to mongoose.
There's database triggers you doing in
Postgress or equivalents in your your
favorite persistence layer. And this is
just going to say before I commit a
transaction, I'm going to go run this
validation at the level and if it
doesn't work, I'm going to fail with uh
you know, I'm going to fail at runtime
with a clear message. Okay. And so what
we want is uh we want mong uh we want
the agent to incorporate this in and
make sure these hooks are used properly
throughout the application within the
shopping cart module. Okay, we don't
want this this invariant doesn't need to
be in all the other aspects of the
shopping cart. It's scoped to this
project to this to this set of functions
module within the project. Okay. And
then we show an example where um we just
ask you know claude to do an analysis
and see how we are against this and then
it detects where we had a miss and now
it goes and it starts creating those and
it'll it'll go and and fix that for us.
Okay. And you can imagine a similar
invariance for the other schemas in the
system.
And so showed three different ways,
three different techniques, three
different scopes. There's a lot of
different appro other approaches you can
take to check the the invariant to
enforce it. How do you instruct it? But
this structure that we put together we
found has been uh it's it's been quite
effective for what we've been working
on. So I want to give everyone some
action plan. I want to give some
homework for folks. Um and it was the
end of the day. So this will stick with
you as you go to the party. So you'll be
sitting there saying, "What did the
credential folks say I should be doing
tonight?" Oh yes. So what we'd ask of
the group
um cope with three things in your you
know that you're working on maybe
feature level module level work what are
three things like you wish that the
agent just stopped doing or started
doing for you think about the framework
that we put together again go download
the stuff there's plenty of examples
just take the template in there's
instructions on how to get uh there's an
agents MD that you can just feed in in
yours and it'll get the the agents to
start using the things and what are
three three things you want to get drop
that into your system, start playing
with it and just look at the before and
after difference. Okay, very simple uh
steps here. Okay, then this month. So
now, okay, this week it's uh what's
today's Wednesday? Wednesday. Okay, so
that's this week. You get the next
month. We got a couple holidays in
there, but you got tie in the next
month. So
uh what you want to do is start building
that a little more and get some better
verification using this on your
codebase. think about uh what things do
I want to block in in the CI/CD process?
What things do I want to prevent from
merging? Okay, so you can use the agent
to go and and put these checks in place
into git if you want or you could
operate operationalize other processes
in your org. Then this quarter start to
build out invariant library, right?
Start to incorporate this into your your
design process. Start to get the the
agents to create the invariants for you
as you go along with it. instructed as
part of your spectriven development and
start to get the benefits through this.
So I'm gonna turn it back to Jennifer
for the end.
>> So um you know what we showed today is
really a tool uh that you can start
using uh immediately uh that you can
leverage in your coding practices today.
Um at Credential we are building a
solution that identifies this class of
bug these types of issues um as well as
many other functional logic memory
safety bugs as well. So if you're
interested to learn more about what
we're building and how we're doing it
without having to deploy, test, execute
your code, um you can find us at
credential.ai. Um we have our weight
list up and ready on our website. So
please reach out. We'd love to uh chat
more.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. So much
[music]
heat.